大家好,欢迎来到真相脱稿
Hello everyone, welcome to "The Truth Unscripted".
今天我们要讲一个在中国不能公开讨论的故事
Today we are going to talk about a story that cannot be openly discussed in China.
1989年的春天,北京天安门广场挤满了人
In the spring of 1989, Tiananmen Square in Beijing was packed with people.
学生、老师、市民,成千上万的人走上街头
Students, teachers, and citizens, tens of thousands of people take to the streets.
喊出了反腐败、要自由、要民主这些口号
Shouting slogans against corruption, calling for freedom and democracy.
他们没带武器,只带着理想
They did not bring weapons, only ideals.
他们希望用最和平的方式
They hope to do it in the most peaceful way.
推动国家往更开放、更公平的方向走
Push the country towards a more open and fair direction.
但那一夜,枪声打断了希望
But that night, gunshots shattered hope.
坦克碾碎了理想
The tank crushed the dream.
这段历史后来被政府刻意删除
This part of history was deliberately erased by the government later on.
连六四这两个字,在中国都成了禁忌
The two words "June Fourth" have become taboo in China.
今天我们就来一起还原那场
Today, let's come together to reenact that scene.
震撼中国震动世界的真实世界
The real world that shocks China and shakes the world.
天安门广场屠杀事件
Tiananmen Square Massacre
要理解1989年为什么会发生这么大规模的抗议
To understand why such a large-scale protest occurred in 1989.
我们得先回头看看那个年代的中国
We need to take a look back at China in that era first.
那时候的中国刚经历改革开放10年
At that time, China had just gone through ten years of reform and opening up.
经济开始腾飞,街上有了个体户
The economy started to take off, and individual businesses began to appear on the streets.
家里能看踩电了
The power is out at home.
很多人的生活得到了一定的改善
Many people's lives have been improved to a certain extent.
代引出现了很多问题
"COD payment method encountered many issues."
通货膨胀厉害,物价飞涨,工资却跟不上
Inflation is severe, prices are soaring, but wages cannot keep up.
更严重的是,贪污腐败越来越严重
More seriously, corruption is becoming increasingly severe.
老百姓怨气越来越大
The anger of the common people is growing.
尤其是年轻人、大学生们,他们受过教育
Especially young people, college students, they have received education.
对国家抱有希望
Have hope for the country.
但也看得见现实的荒诞
But you can also see the absurdity of reality.
他们想问问题,想参与,想发声
They want to ask questions, to participate, to speak up.
就在这个时候,1989年4月15日
Just at this moment, April 15, 1989.
前中共总书记胡耀邦去世了
Former General Secretary of the Communist Party of China, Hu Yaobang, passed away.
他在大家心中是个开明的领导人
He is seen as an open-minded leader by everyone.
他支持言论自由,反对打压学生
He supports freedom of speech and opposes the suppression of students.
很多人怀念他,不仅因为他的死
Many people miss him, not only because of his death.
也因为他代表了一种被冲劫的希望
Also because he represents a hope that has been robbed.
所以北京的大学生们
"So Beijing's college students"
开始自发组织去天安门广场悼念
Start organizing spontaneously to mourn at Tiananmen Square.
打着横幅写着标语
Displaying banners with slogans.
但这不是单纯的哀悼
But this is not simply mourning.
那股情绪很快就变成了对现实不满的表达
That emotion quickly turned into an expression of dissatisfaction with reality.
学生们开始提出要求
Students are starting to make demands.
反腐、新闻自由、民主改革、公开官员财产等等
anti-corruption, freedom of the press, democratic reform, disclosure of officials' assets, and so on
他们不是在闹事
They are not causing trouble.
他们是在争取一种他们相信国家应该有的未来
They are striving for a future that they believe the country should have.
特别的是,这种呼声很快得到了普通市民的支持
特别的是,这种呼声很快得到了普通市民的支持。
Especially, this call quickly gained the support of ordinary citizens.
连工人、老师、医生、各行各业的人都站出来参加了他们
Even workers, teachers, doctors, and people from various professions all came forward to participate in it.
一场全国性的政治觉醒
A national political awakening
就这样从悼念一个领导人
Just like that, mourning a leader.
变成了中国历史上最大规模的一次集体呐喊
It has become the largest collective shout in Chinese history.
很快,天安门广场上的人越来越多
Soon, there are more and more people on Tiananmen Square.
规模越来越大
The scale is getting bigger and bigger.
学生们不只是去悼念
Students are not only going to mourn.
他们在广场上搭了棚子
They set up a tent on the square.
设了广播站
Set up a broadcasting station.
举着写满诉求的横幅
Holding a banner filled with appeals.
还组建了学生自治联合会
The student autonomous union was also formed.
开始有组织的行动起来
Start to organize and take action.
他们喊的口号其实不起端
The slogan they are shouting is actually not constructive.
全是宪法里面写的东西
Everything is written in the constitution.
要新闻自由
"要新闻自由" in English is "Freedom of the press is essential".
要政府反腐败
Demand the government to fight against corruption.
要和学生代表对话
To have a conversation with the student representative
你会发现他们没有任何暴力行为
You will find that they have no violent behavior.
顶多是喊喊口号
At most, it's just shouting slogans.
写写标语
Write some slogans.
拉拉横幅
拉拉横幅 translates to "pull up the banner" in English.
这放在今天
This is for today.
连个微博热搜都上不了
Can't even make it to the trending list on Weibo.
然后发生了一件很重要的大事
Then a very important event occurred.
绝食
fasting
5月13日
May 13th
几百个学生宣布开始绝食
Hundreds of students declared a hunger strike.
他们说我们不用暴力
They said we don't need to use violence.
但用身体唤醒国家良知
Awaken the nation's conscience with the body.
这不是作秀
This is not a show.
是因为他们真的觉得
It is because they really feel.
如果不这样
If not like this.
没人会听他们说话
No one will listen to them speak.
绝食消息出影响非常大
The news of the hunger strike has had a significant impact.
很多普通市民开始送水
Many ordinary citizens have started to deliver water.
送食物
Deliver food.
甚至把孩子也带到广场上来看学生
Even bring the children to the square to watch the students.
他们觉得这些孩子太勇敢了
They think these children are too brave.
说出了所有人的心声
Voicing the thoughts of everyone.
然后就出现了那段历史上
Then that segment appeared in history.
非常著名的一幕
A very famous scene
赵紫阳走进了广场
Zhao Ziyang walked into the square.
1989年5月19日
May 19, 1989
他已经快被政治边缘化了
He has been almost politically marginalized.
但他还是来了
But he still came.
他拿着扩音器声音哽咽地说
He spoke hoarsely through the microphone.
你们还年轻
You are still young.
身体是革命的本钱
The body is the capital of the revolution.
他说完就走了
He left right after he finished speaking.
那一刻有些人哭了
At that moment, some people cried.
有些人不理解
Some people do not understand.
有些人觉得希望快要熄灭了
Some people feel like their hope is fading away.
结果第二天
the next day
政府就宣布北京戒严
The government declared martial law in Beijing.
这不是开玩笑
This is not a joke.
是全国十几个军区的部队
It is a military force from several military regions across the country.
开始进入北京
Enter Beijing开始
目标是天安门广场
The goal is Tiananmen Square.
而学生们也进入了最关键的时刻
And the students have also entered the most critical moment.
他们开始感受到紧张
They start to feel nervous.
但也没有选择离开
But there is also no choice but to stay.
他们以为和平理性坚持
They believe in peace, reason, and perseverance.
就能感动政府
Can move the government.
但其实政府已经做了另外一种决定
But in fact, the government has made another decision.
5月下旬
late May
军队开始陆续向北京集结
The army has started to gather in Beijing one after another.
准备执行戒严
Prepare to impose martial law.
你可以想象
You can imagine
北京的街头
The streets of Beijing
突然出现了装甲车、军车、士兵
Suddenly there appeared armored vehicles, military vehicles, and soldiers.
气氛一下子变了
The atmosphere suddenly changed.
但让人震撼的是
But what is truly astonishing is
北京市民的反应
The reaction of Beijing residents.
数以万计的普通人自发走上街头
Tens of thousands of ordinary people took to the streets spontaneously.
拦住军车
Stop the military vehicle.
有的直接躺在马路上
Some of them are directly lying on the road.
有的把自行车、公交车排在一起
Some place bicycles and buses together.
组成路障
set up roadblock
有人甚至劝士兵
Some even advise the soldiers.
你们是人民的军队
"You are the army of the people."
不应该对我们开枪
Should not shoot at us.
很多军人也懵了
Many soldiers were also left dumbfounded.
他们根本不知道自己来干嘛
They have no idea what they are here for.
他们以为是来维持秩序
They thought they were there to maintain order.
结果被老百姓挡着
The result was blocked by the common people.
一时间也不敢贸然前进
I dare not move forward rashly for the time being.
于是军队被卡在北京周边这几个城区
The army was stranded in the surrounding districts of Beijing.
士兵只能住在车上
Soldiers can only live in their vehicles.
睡在郊外
Sleeping in the outskirts.
情绪一天比一天焦躁
Emotions are becoming more and more irritable day by day.
而广场上的学生呢
And what about the students on the square?
他们没看到军队
They did not see the army.
但能感受到紧张的气氛
but can feel the tense atmosphere
他们开始讨论是不是该撤退
They began to discuss whether they should retreat.
是不是谈判还有希望
Is there still hope for negotiation?
但最终大多数人选择了留下
But in the end, most people chose to stay.
因为他们相信我们是正义的
Because they believe that we are righteous.
是和平的
It is peaceful.
政府不会对我们开枪
The government will not shoot at us.
他们可能低估了这个体制
They may have underestimated this system.
对权力的坚持
Persistence in power
远远超过了对生命的尊重
Far beyond mere respect for life.
到了6月初
In early June.
政府已经做出了决定
The government has made a decision.
不惜一切代价清场
Clear the field at all costs.
1989年6月3日晚上
the evening of June 3, 1989
北京的街头越来越紧张
The streets in Beijing are getting increasingly tense.
从四面八方军队开始重新推进
The army from all directions is starting to advance again.
这一次他们不再克制
This time they no longer hold back.
带的是屎弹
The thing brought is a poop bomb.
士兵还是上街了
The soldiers took to the streets.
他们以为还能像上次那样
They think they can still do it like last time.
用身体挡住军车
Use your body to block the military vehicle.
但这回不同了
But this time it's different.
军队开枪了
The military opened fire.
最早在穆西地就传来了枪声
Gunshots were first heard in Mosul.
不是打天
Not striking the heavens.
而是朝人群扫射
instead, shooting into the crowd
很多人根本没想到会真打
Many people never thought it would actually come to a real fight.
有的甚至还在劝士兵冷静
Some are even persuading the soldiers to stay calm.
却当场中弹倒下
"But fell to the ground under fire on the spot."
有人倒下
Someone has fallen.
有人去救人
Someone is going to rescue people.
结果也被打到
The result was also affected.
那一晚
那一晚 -> That night
北京的夜空下
Under the night sky of Beijing
传出的是枪声
The sound of gunfire can be heard.
哭声和尖叫
The sound of crying and screaming
广场外围已成了战场
The perimeter of the square has become a battlefield.
军队沿街推进
The army advances along the street.
装甲车碾压障碍
Armored vehicle crushes obstacles.
市民们四散奔逃
The citizens scattered and fled.
而天安门广场的中心
The center of Tiananmen Square
学生们所在的地方
The place where the students are.
其实还不知道外面发生了什么
Actually, I don't know what's going on outside yet.
他们听到远处有响动
They heard noise coming from a distance.
但搞不清状况
But unclear about the situation.
凌晨一点
1 o'clock in the morning
军队包围了广场
The army surrounded the square.
广播里开始喊话
The announcement started on the radio.
请学生立刻撤离
Please evacuate the students immediately.
学生代表们商量后决定
The student representatives discussed and decided.
我们走
We are leaving.
但希望留下广场上的民主女神像
But hope to leave the Statue of Liberty in the square.
士兵没说话
The soldier did not speak.
直接开始强行清场
Directly start the forced clearance.
有人记得有人拍下照片
Some people remember, some people take photos.
但很多画面再也见不到了
But many scenes can no longer be seen.
当广场终于被清空
When the square was finally cleared.
天已经亮了
The day has already dawned.
地面被冲洗过
The ground has been washed.
血迹被盖住
Cover up the bloodstains.
帐篷 标语 遗物
tent, slogan, relic
全都不见了
All gone.
可就在6月5日
On June 5th.
一个小小的动作震惊了世界
A small action shocked the world.
一个年轻人
a young person
提着两个塑料袋
Carrying two plastic bags.
站在长安街的车道上
Standing on the lane of Chang'an Street.
挡在一排坦克面前
Standing in front of a row of tanks.
他不动 坦克想绕开他
He is not moving, and the tank is trying to go around him.
他再过去继续挡
He moved forward to continue blocking.
这个画面被拍下
This scene was captured on camera.
传遍全球
Spread worldwide.
他被叫做坦克人
He is called Tank Man.
没人知道他是谁
No one knows who he is.
也没人知道他后来怎么样了
No one knows what happened to him later.
有人说他被抓了
Someone said he was caught.
有人说他被杀了
Someone said he was killed.
有人说他活着 只是不敢出声
Some say he is alive, but dare not speak.
但他那一战
"But his battle"
让全世界记住了
Let the world remember.
中国政府不是驱散人群
The Chinese government does not disperse crowds.
是用军队镇压
Suppress with the military.
而是自己的人民
but their own people
清场之后 政府没有道歉
After clearing the scene, the government did not apologize.
没有解释
No explanation.
相反 他们开始了一场全面的清洗
On the contrary, they initiated a thorough cleansing.
先是抓人
First thing's first, catch the person.
参与学运的学生
Students participating in the student movement.
被列入通缉名单
being on the wanted list
21名学生头目被全国通缉
21 students leaders have been put on the national wanted list.
柴林 吴尔开西
Chai Lin Wuerkaixi
这些人通过地下渠道
These people are using underground channels.
逃到了国外
escaped to another country
这就是所谓的黄雀行动
This is the so-called Operation Yellowbird.
但大多数普通人
but the majority of ordinary people
没有这么幸运
Not so lucky.
有的因为当晚上街救人
Some people go out to the streets at night to save others.
被捕
arrested
有的因为给学生送水
Some because of delivering water to students.
送药被判刑
Sentenced to prison for delivering medicine.
然后控制舆论
Then control public opinion.
央视报纸统一口径
Central Television and newspapers maintain a unified stance.
说是平息反革命暴乱
To say to quell the counter-revolutionary riot.
全国媒体一夜之间
Overnight, national media
变成了一种声音
Turned into a sound.
再后来就是我们现在看到的
After that, it's what we see now.
彻底封锁信息
Completely block information.
从1990年代开始
Since the 1990s.
课本里再也看不到
The textbook is no longer in sight.
天安门事件这几个字
The Tiananmen Square Incident
在2000年以后
after the year 2000
连在网上搜索64
Searching for "64" online.
1989坦克人
Tank Man in 1989
都直接跳出错误页
"都直接跳出错误页" 可以翻译为 "All directly jump out of the error page"
甚至封号
even banned
有段时间网友
For a period of time, internet users.
发5月35日
"发5月35日" translates to "Issue on May 35th" in English.
来代指6月4日
June 4th
结果连35都成了敏感词
The result is that even "35" has become a sensitive word.
微信 微博 知乎
WeChat, Weibo, Zhihu
百度全都不允许讨论
Baidu does not allow any discussion at all.
谁敢发言
"Who dares to speak?"
很可能被警告 伤害
Very likely to be warned of harm.
甚至拘留
even detention
是删帖还是删记忆
Is it deleting a post or erasing a memory?
现在很多00后
Many people born in the 2000s now.
10后 甚至连64
10 even 64
是什么都不知道
knows nothing
他们从小在一个过滤过的
They grew up in a sheltered environment.
系统里长大
Grow up in the system.
被教育国家越来越强大
The educated countries are becoming stronger and stronger.
党是我们最亲的妈妈
The party is our dearest mother.
但那些曾经发生过的事
The things that happened in the past.
真的能被永远删除吗
Can it really be permanently deleted?
很多人说中国变强了
Many people say that China has become stronger.
发展了
developed
这30多年变化翻天覆地
The changes over the past 30 years have been earth-shaking.
但我们想问一个
But we would like to ask one question.
更基本的问题
more fundamental issues
中国是不是变得更自由了
Has China become more free now?
回到1989年
Back to 1989.
那个时候没有互联网
At that time, there was no internet.
没有社交媒体
No social media.
甚至连手机都不普及
Even mobile phones are not common.
但学生能走上街头
But students can take to the streets.
市民能一起上广场
Citizens can go to the square together.
媒体还能发评论文章
The media can also publish opinion articles.
大学还能组织学生自治会
The university can also organize a student union.
那时候的大学生
college students at that time
可以公开要求政府反腐
You can publicly demand the government to combat corruption.
可以要求新闻自由
You can demand press freedom.
甚至跟领导人谈判
Even negotiating with the leaders.
赵紫阳是当时的
Zhao Ziyang was at that time.
中共中央总书记
General Secretary of the Communist Party of China (CPC) Central Committee
能走进广场跟学生对话
Be able to enter the square and have a conversation with students.
哪怕最后失败
Even if it ends in failure.
但至少那时候还有对话
But at least there was still dialogue at that time.
不同的领导人之间
Between different leaders
也有路线之争
There is also a dispute over the route.
邓小平李鹏胡耀邦赵紫阳
Deng Xiaoping, Li Peng, Hu Yaobang, Zhao Ziyang
这些领导人对中国的未来
These leaders are shaping the future of China.
都有不同的看法
Different people have different views.
再看看今天的中国
Take another look at China today.
2025年
2025年: 2025
如果你在微博里说了一句六四
If you mention the phrase "June Fourth" on Weibo.
你的账号可能被封
Your account may be suspended.
如果你在街上举了一张白纸
If you hold up a blank piece of paper on the street.
你可能会被寻衅滋事拘留
You may be detained for provocation and causing trouble.
如果你想做一个独立的
If you want to be independent.
播客节目
podcast program
你可能连上传的机会都没有
You may not even have the chance to upload.
新闻统一口径
Unified news narrative
大学全面挡管
The university provides comprehensive counseling services.
民营企业被要求建立党支部
Private enterprises are required to establish party branches.
外企纷纷撤离
Foreign companies are withdrawing one after another.
网络关键词全部封杀
All key internet search terms are banned.
普通人一不小心
One careless move by an ordinary person
就会被喝茶
Will be invited for tea
在习近平的亲自指挥
under the personal command of Xi Jinping
亲自指挥亲自领导下
Directly supervise and lead personally.
疫情期间的封城
Lockdown during the pandemic.
核酸方舱
nucleic acid cabin
贵州大巴
Guizhou coach/bus
新疆大火
The Xinjiang fire
上海这样的国际都市也会饿死人
A cosmopolitan city like Shanghai can also leave people hungry.
但是在中国的任何媒体上
However, in any media in China.
无人干演
The performance is unmanned.
那种窒息感
That suffocating feeling.
不是因为没人想说话
It's not because no one wants to talk.
而是说话要付出代价
It costs to speak.
所以你说
"So you say"
这算不算退步
Does this count as a regression?
改革开放几十年后
Decades after the Reform and Opening-up.
经济却是发展了
The economy has developed.
基础建设很漂亮
The infrastructure is very nice.
城市灯火辉煌
The city lights are magnificent.
但是自由的空间
However, space of freedom.
反而越缩越小
The more you retreat, the smaller you become.
很多年轻人
Many young people
甚至不知道六四是什么
Don't even know what June 4th means.
搜索不出来
"Cannot find in search results"
书本不提
Books are not mentioned.
长辈也不敢讲
Even the elders dare not speak.
这不是忘记
This is not forgetting.
这是被安排的事宜
This is an arranged matter.
我们不是在贩卖情绪
We are not selling emotions.
也不是在否定一切
It's not denying everything either.
如果一个社会不能讨论自己的历史
If a society cannot discuss its own history
那它就很难
It would be very difficult.
走向真正的未来
Towards a Real Future
从广场到白纸
From the square to the blank paper.
从绝食到沉默
From Fasting to Silence.
这不是进步
This is not progress.
是退步
regress
但只要还有人在讲
But as long as someone is still speaking
就说明这个国家
Just describe this country.
还没有完全放弃希望
Not completely giving up hope yet.